<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="preface-copyright" role="copyrightpg">
  <title>Copyright</title>

  <para>Copyright 2013 ff4j</para>

  <para>Online version published by Cedrick LUNVEN</para>

  <para>Java(TM) and all Java-based trademarks and logos are trademarks or
  registered trademarks of Sun Microsystems, Inc., in the United States and
  other countries. Many of the designations used by manufacturers and sellers
  to distinguish their products are claimed as trademarks. Where those
  designations appear in this book, and Logica, was aware of a
  trademark claim, the designations have been printed in caps or initial
  caps.</para>

  <para>While every precaution has been taken in the preparation of this book,
  the publisher and authors assume no responsibility for errors or omissions,
  or for damages resulting from the use of the information contained
  herein.</para>

    <para>This work is licensed under Apache2</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>You must attribute the work to Logica, Inc. with a link to
        <ulink
        url="http://www.sonatype.com">http://www.logica.com</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You may not use this work for commercial purposes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You may not alter, transform, or build upon this work.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>1. Licence : </para>
    
    <para>2. Restrictions.
	Licensee shall not modify, copy, </para>
		
	<para>3. Warranty of Title.
	 Developer hereby represents and warrants to Licensee that Developer is the owner of the Software or otherwise
	 has the right to grant to Licensee the rights set forth in this Agreement. In the event any breach or threatened
	 breach of the foregoing representation and warranty, Licensee's sole remedy shall be to require Developer or to
	 either: i) procure, at Developer's expense, the right to use the Software, ii) replace the Software or any part
	 thereof that is in breach and replace it with Software of comparable functionality that does not cause any breach,
	 or iii) refund to Licensee the full amount of the license fee upon the return of the Software and all copies
	 thereof to Developer.
	</para>    
   
</preface>
