<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="preface">
  <title>Preface</title>
  
  <para>The aim of this document is to provide an effective guide for developers to help
  them using the Logica Business Process Management Framework.
  </para>
  
  <section id="preface-section-how-to-use">
  	<title>How to use this book ?</title>   	
   	<para>
   	 If you are novice and want be initiated to framework you can use the getting starter chapter.
  	</para>  	
  	<para>
  	If you already have some experience with BPM tools and want to improve your skills
  	you can read the chapter upon advanced concept.
  	</para>  	
  	<para>
  	For  deployment issues please refer to Installation procedure, setting up section, 
  	exploitation and administration chapters.
  	</para>  	
  </section>  
  
  <!-- Convention de polices -->
  <section id="preface-section-fontConventions">
    <title>Font conventions</title>

    <para>
     The book follows naming conventions and font usage. Understanding these conventions up-front makes
    it easier to read this book.
    </para>

    <!-- Italique -->
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis role="italic">Italic</emphasis>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Used for filenames, file extensions, url, application names,
            important terms and finally keywords and first appearance of new terms.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><literal moreinfo="none">Constant width</literal></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used for Java class names, methods, variables, properties,
          data types, database elements, and snippets of code that appear in
          text.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold"> <literal moreinfo="none">Constant width
        bold</literal> </emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used for commands you enter at the command line and to
          highlight new code inserted in a running example.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="italic"> <literal moreinfo="none">Constant width
        italic</literal> </emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used to annotate output.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  
  <section id="preface-section--contactUs">
    <title>How to Contact Us</title>

    <para>To comment or ask for technical support about this book, send email
    to:</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para><emphasis role="italic"> <email>bpf.support@logica.com</email>
      </emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>
   
  </section>

  <section id="preface-section-acknowledgements">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <para>Logica would like to thank the following contributors. The people
    listed below have provide feedback which has helped improve the quality of
    this book. Thanks to Laurent Gauthier, Yohann Botquelen and Gary Grandjean.
    </para>
  </section>
</preface>
